<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel><title>Johan Renaudie - Blog</title><link>https://plannapus.github.io/blog/index.html</link><description>A little bit of science, a little bit of programming, a little bit of cooking...</description>
<item><title>First step in mixing gplates and R to make paleogeographic maps</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-15.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-15</pubDate><description>I make a lot of paleogeographic maps, and I always do so in R. Whichever way you do, Gplates is an invaluable tool to do so. What follows is a short exampleas mentioned in the previous post I am still processing some bad news so it's all I am capable of conjuring right now of how to insert it in your workflow to map your paleodata.</description><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>Guinea Fowl in Cider</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-10.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-10</pubDate><description>As every time I receive bad news, I cope by cooking. This weekend, I wanted to try something new so I did the lazy variation of inventing a new dish: combining two dishes.</description></item>
<item><title>A walk through my beamer theme</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-05.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-05</pubDate><description>A few years ago I started converting to LaTeX: first for proposals, manuscripts and then eventually for presentations. I am not going to lie: the first one took me way longer than usual but since then, now that I have a basic template, it became really worth it. I didn't go for a flashy, fancy theme but made a very simple one based on my institution official template. And since it is simple, it makes for a nice introduction to people willing to learn how to make their own beamer template. </description><category>Latex</category></item>
<item><title>A backbone for radiolarian phylogeny</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-02.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-02</pubDate><description>It's been a couple of good years for radiolarian research! After almost 200 years of studying them, and failing to understand their classification fully (in part thanks to Haeckel honestly), three papers came out in the last 2 years that present molecular data to establish a proper backbone to living radiolarian phylogeny. </description></item>
<item><title>Scraping rendered HTML</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-09-28.html</link><pubDate>2020-09-28</pubDate><description>Once in a while (or, you know, every day), when you're doing 'big' data analysis you need to do some web scraping – grab directly data from public websites – particularly if they do not have an API to deliver the data you are interested in. Most of the time, all it takes is to read in the HTML page in R (thanks to package XML), and pick up the data, which in the best case scenario already lies there as a table. </description><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>A little bit of everything</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-09-27.html</link><pubDate>2020-09-27</pubDate><description>Since a few months, I felt the need to create a blog. I have literally no idea why. Nor have I any idea of what I will put in it, though if I had to guess I would say a little bit of science — most probably the day-to-day somewhat boring details of it —, a little bit of programming — I have been contributing to StackOverflow for years, and I have been helping my colleagues a lot with their programming, but this way I might actually talk about the issues I want to talk about and not the ones I am asked about —, a little bit of cooking — as it is a significant part of my life and the one that is the easiest to talk about and the most likely to actually interest someone else than myself :) — and maybe a little bit about other subjects that interest me – literature, board games, mythology, ...</description></item>
</channel>
</rss>
