<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel><title>Johan Renaudie - Blog</title><link>https://plannapus.github.io/blog/index.html</link><description>A little bit of science, a little bit of programming, a little bit of cooking...</description>
<item><title>Advent of Code 2020</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-30.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-30</pubDate><description>Tomorrow starts the best advent event of the year: the Advent of Code!</description><category>Programming</category></item>
<item><title>Some fried rice recipe I started making during the first lockdown</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-22.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-22</pubDate><description>As most people wh-o ended home and aimless during the first lockdown, I cooked a bit more than usual and attempted new recipes. Now that we are in a second lockdown (albeit a so-called 'lite lockdown'), after almost a year of not leaving Berlin and not seeing my family I tend to crave for more rustic french cuisine, but I do occasionally cook those recipes I came up with during the first lockdown. Three of them were good enough for me to write them down: one is a fried rice recipe, while the two others are spring recipes so not necessarily interesting for the time being (a recipe of pasta with squids and another of an eggplant-based sauce for pasta as well).</description><category>Cooking</category></item>
<item><title>A look at the code behing the blog</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-20.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-20</pubDate><description>This is going to be very meta, I'm afraid. In the first post of this blog I said that I wasn't sure why I was doing this. Two months later, I am still not entirely sure of my motivation (though being fairly obsessive it allows me to put all my thoughts somewhere instead of rehashing them constantly in my mind, so it does help with that) but I know that one of the small reason was to see if I was able to write down a very simple code to write a functional blog.</description><category>Programming</category><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>TMS General Meeting 2020 Online</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-13.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-13</pubDate><description>This week was the annual meeting of The Micropalaeontological Society, in fact it doubled as its 50th anniversary. Of course given the current nightmare circumstances, it happened online and I must say that of all the many, many, MANY meetings and conferences I attended online this year, this might have been one of the most well done, together with the EGU online meeting which was really cool and original as it was really free-form, whereas TMS did manage to stick successfully to the classic talks + posters setting. </description><category>Science</category></item>
<item><title>Calculating paleocoordinates with gplates and R</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-09.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-09</pubDate><description>As promised in the first post of this series, I am going to show here how to use gplates to calculate the paleocoordinates of specific sites given a specific rotation model, using GPlates. To make it worth it, I'll use here the Matthews et al. 2016 rotation model as it is an update on the one we are using in the Neptune database. Also, and just for fun, we are going to compute the paleocoordinates of the two sites we drilled during Expedition 379 to the Amundsen Sea, an expedition I was part of. We only drilled until the latest Miocene but here I am going to compute the coordinates in the Turonian (as a tribute to the Klages et al. 2020 paper).</description><category>Programming</category><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>Addendum to the previous post on paleogeographic maps</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-11-03.html</link><pubDate>2020-11-03</pubDate><description>As it turned out, I realized the way I have been making maps in R since 10 years is more or less deprecated! Package sp was superseded by package sf, and indeed the coordinate system transformation works so much better and do not need as much weird hacking to work on complex projections.</description><category>Programming</category><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>A few thoughts on stratigraphy</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-28.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-28</pubDate><description>This summer Dave and I wrote a pre-proposal for a pilote project (whose goal was to create a data standard for stratigraphy) in the context of the NFDI4Earth, a german-wide initiative to create a common infrastructure for geosciences-related research data. </description><category>Science</category></item>
<item><title>Sarah's paper in Nature Communications</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-22.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-22</pubDate><description>At last, our paper, lead by Sarah Trubovitz, came out today in Nature Communications ! Sarah came to visit us in Berlin twice in 2017 to learn/figure out with us the taxonomy of Neogene radiolarians from the equatorial Pacific. We had an inkling that the actual amount of species in that region/timeframe would be way higher that what was published but I must admit we did't expect that much: she found 990 species just in the last 10 million years of a single site!</description><category>Science</category></item>
<item><title>Miassou</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-21.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-21</pubDate><description>The region I come from is known for its duck/goose-based cooking, not so much for its desserts. And indeed we do not have that much of a sweet tooth in Perigord Noir. But we do have a few desserts. My favourite and maybe the least known of them is the miassou, and I happen to make quite a good one, if i may say so. The name unfortunately refers to a dozen different dishes, ranging from potato pancakes to any cornmeal-based cake, so what follows is a recipe of miassou, as done in my family.</description><category>Cooking</category></item>
<item><title>First step in mixing gplates and R to make paleogeographic maps</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-15.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-15</pubDate><description>I make a lot of paleogeographic maps, and I always do so in R. Whichever programming language you use, Gplates is an invaluable tool to achieve this. What follows is a short exampleas mentioned in the previous post I am still processing some bad news so it's all I am capable of conjuring right now of how to insert it in your workflow to map your paleodata.</description><category>Programming</category><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>Guinea Fowl in Cider</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-10.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-10</pubDate><description>As every time I receive bad news, I cope by cooking. This weekend, I wanted to try something new so I did the lazy variation of inventing a new dish: combining two dishes.</description><category>Cooking</category></item>
<item><title>A walk through my beamer theme</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-05.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-05</pubDate><description>A few years ago I started converting to LaTeX: first for proposals, manuscripts and then eventually for presentations. I am not going to lie: the first one took me way longer than usual but since then, now that I have a basic template, it became really worth it. I didn't go for a flashy, fancy theme but made a very simple one based on my institution official template. And since it is simple, it makes for a nice introduction to people willing to learn how to make their own beamer template. </description><category>Programming</category><category>LaTeX</category></item>
<item><title>A backbone for radiolarian phylogeny</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-10-02.html</link><pubDate>2020-10-02</pubDate><description>It's been a couple of good years for radiolarian research! After almost 200 years of studying them, and failing to understand their classification fully (in part thanks to Haeckel honestly), three papers came out in the last 2 years that present molecular data to establish a proper backbone to living radiolarian phylogeny. </description><category>Science</category></item>
<item><title>Scraping rendered HTML</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-09-28.html</link><pubDate>2020-09-28</pubDate><description>Once in a while (or, you know, every day), when you're doing 'big' data analysis you need to do some web scraping – grab directly data from public websites – particularly if they do not have an API to deliver the data you are interested in. Most of the time, all it takes is to read in the HTML page in R (thanks to package XML), and pick up the data, which in the best case scenario already lies there as a table. </description><category>Programming</category><category>R</category></item>
<item><title>A little bit of everything</title><link>http://plannapus.github.io/blog/2020-09-27.html</link><pubDate>2020-09-27</pubDate><description>Since a few months, I felt the need to create a blog. I have literally no idea why. Nor have I any idea of what I will put in it, though if I had to guess I would say a little bit of science — most probably the day-to-day somewhat boring details of it —, a little bit of programming — I have been contributing to StackOverflow for years, and I have been helping my colleagues a lot with their programming, but this way I might actually talk about the issues I want to talk about and not the ones I am asked about —, a little bit of cooking — as it is a significant part of my life and the one that is the easiest to talk about and the most likely to actually interest someone else than myself :) — and maybe a little bit about other subjects that interest me – literature, board games, mythology, ...</description></item>
</channel>
</rss>
